<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-09T23:43:17+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">iamhasime</title><subtitle>A record of journey of a wannabe entrepreneur</subtitle><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><entry><title type="html">Lessons from June 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/lessons-may-2024-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from June 2024" /><published>2024-06-09T18:01:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-06-09T18:01:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/lessons-may-2024%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/lessons-may-2024-copy.html">&lt;p&gt;tl;dr of the lessons from june, 2024&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-from-the-books-im-reading&quot;&gt;A. From the Books I’m Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25451264-death-s-end&quot;&gt;Rememberance of Earth’s Past - 03 - Death’s End&lt;/a&gt; [21%]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-internet&quot;&gt;B. Internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Appeal for the Un-manly Man&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Four Stages of Cocktail Theory&lt;br /&gt;
This beautiful write-up by the legendary investor Peter Lynch demonstrates the various stages of investing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quartr.com/insights/investment-strategy/the-cocktail-party-theory&quot;&gt;Read on&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Get Busy with life’s purpose, toss aside empty hopes, get active in your own rescue - if you care for yourself at all – and do it while you can.&lt;br /&gt;
– Macrus Aurelius&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">tl;dr of the lessons from june, 2024</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Way of Ideas</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/the-peculier-case-of-ideas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Way of Ideas" /><published>2024-06-09T16:19:04+05:30</published><updated>2024-06-09T16:19:04+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/the-peculier-case-of-ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/06/09/the-peculier-case-of-ideas.html">&lt;p&gt;No idea is a universal idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All ideas have a limited scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ideas, like socialism, work great between a family or a group of friends but fail at a scale of society. Other ideas, like capitalism create wedges between a community but work great in running a country and the world economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, no idea acts in the best interest of everyone. British Imperialism was brutal for India for example. Modern capitalism on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, there are no final ideas – everything is part of a greater unfolding system that builds on top of the existing ideas and keeps piling on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, one might feel that ideas are cyclical rather than incremental. That’s because all good ideas are re-discoverable. Why? Because, all ideas build upon the older ones. Hence, it is imperative that we learn from the earlier mishaps with greater ideas. Totalitarianism is one such idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas are time-dependent too. Because humans forget and omit all the time, as and when the times repeat themselves, so do the ideas coming out of that time. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Renaissance&quot;&gt;The Italian Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; is a great example of it. It built upon the already explored arts by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_antiquity&quot;&gt;Ancient Rome&lt;/a&gt; – after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_Ages_(historiography)&quot;&gt;“Dark Ages”&lt;/a&gt;; a gap of over 10 centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest fallacy of our (and every) time is that the ideas of today are the most complete ideas. Wars have been fought over this one mirage. Modern feminism movement is an example of such a social war. But most bloody are people with new ideas becoming violent to vindicate their new ideas. History is littered with such revolutionary “saviors” leading masses to their communal grave with their new, shiny ideas – China, Russia, Korea, Vietnam are the recent examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the most tricky are the ideas of the bygone era, taking shape as the ultimate truth. Modern religious wars are a great example of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, in each context, all ideas are valid. And in all scales, all ideas are fallible. It is up to us, the bearers of our current world to understand this not be lost in the reflection of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">No idea is a universal idea.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from March 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/30/lessons-may-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from March 2024" /><published>2024-05-30T19:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-05-30T19:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/30/lessons-may-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/30/lessons-may-2024.html">&lt;p&gt;tl;dr of the lessons from may, 2024&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-from-the-books-im-reading&quot;&gt;A. From the Books I’m Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20518872-the-three-body-problem&quot;&gt;Rememberance of Earth’s Past - 01 - The Three-Body Problem&lt;/a&gt;  [read]
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23168817-the-dark-forest&quot;&gt;Rememberance of Earth’s Past - 02 - The Dark Foresh&lt;/a&gt;  [read]
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25451264-death-s-end&quot;&gt;Rememberance of Earth’s Past - 03 - Death’s End&lt;/a&gt; [10%]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-internet&quot;&gt;B. Internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Demon Core&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Australian Bank Note for AUD 100&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Determinism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">tl;dr of the lessons from may, 2024</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Achilles’ Heel Trait</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/25/achilles-heel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Achilles’ Heel Trait" /><published>2024-05-25T16:04:04+05:30</published><updated>2024-05-25T16:04:04+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/25/achilles-heel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/05/25/achilles-heel.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-prioritise-your-mental-peace-by-forgiving-others-shortcomings&quot;&gt;How to prioritise your mental-peace by forgiving others’ “shortcomings”.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of growing up is spending more time with yourself. One downstream effect of this is a higher sense of individuality and symbolically, a heightened selectivity in the type of people you want around yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, although the alignment between people is rising due to closer knit echo-chambers on the internet and broader acceptance of differing ideas - there’s always someone who’ll just hate the existence of, someone whose existence just irks you beyond comparison..and you don’t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No human trait is original, all that we are is an inherited copy of our parents, the society we lived in, a social class we grew in, if lucky a rich heritage, some traditions that makes us a part of a broader family, and some tribe – nation, state, language, heroes, stories etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all this randomness, and uniqueness in the levels and breadth of perception, it is very far-fetched to expect 100% alignment from people. Further futile is people deteriorating their relationships, expectations because of these mis-alignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, below are the two axioms that have worked for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Internal peace should be the primary goal of our sustenance – it’s too important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone, including you, WILL have an Achilles’ heel trait about them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way that I’ve found to live a peaceful life without letting the “obvious BS” of the world get to me is these two axioms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True maturity is making allowances for others’ Achilles’ heel traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you learn to discount the obvious Achilles’ heel trait of a person, you’ll find a great deal of freedom and joy in the company of most people. A complex being like the guy next you can’t just be shrugged off and equated to null-value because “you didn’t like the way they didn’t call you, after they said they would”, or “they talked bad about you behind your back” – your internal peace is too important for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’ll always be some people who will find contentment is harbouring offence or just the opposite, malice for others – those people will never find the peace that they are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the top tier greatness is making arrangements for your Achilles’ heel trait when dealing with other people. Consideration, afterall, is the highest form of love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you’ve a great one!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">How to prioritise your mental-peace by forgiving others’ “shortcomings”. Part of growing up is spending more time with yourself. One downstream effect of this is a higher sense of individuality and symbolically, a heightened selectivity in the type of people you want around yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Marraige</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/04/01/why-marriage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Marraige" /><published>2024-04-01T09:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-04-01T09:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/04/01/why-marriage</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/04/01/why-marriage.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-term-relationship-with-long-term-people&quot;&gt;long term relationship with long-term people.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculus is a way of deciphering an instantenous value of a long-term function.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">long term relationship with long-term people.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from March 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/03/30/lessons-mar-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from March 2024" /><published>2024-03-30T09:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-30T09:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/03/30/lessons-mar-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/03/30/lessons-mar-2024.html">&lt;p&gt;tl;dr of the lessons from this month&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-from-the-books-im-reading&quot;&gt;A. From the Books I’m Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20518872-the-three-body-problem&quot;&gt;The Three-Body Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-internet&quot;&gt;B. Internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;True Masculinity
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Masculintity is not the opposite of Feminity. Boyish immaturitity in the opposite of masculinity.&lt;br /&gt;
Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/IzINu0wezWU?si=zexX6qgRdx3YWxwi&amp;amp;t=42&quot;&gt;Why Iroh is the Pinnacle of Masculinity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up, I was always confused on what being a man truly meant. I grew up on movies from the 90s and the masculinity shown in those, reviewing them today .. who tf was writing them. TV (up until very recently), society, &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; homes were never the ideal places to figure out masculintity and in such a sphere we were expected to behave &lt;em&gt;respectfully&lt;/em&gt; with the other half? No wonder we’re in such a sad spot on the timeline. India still fares VERY low (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pib.gov.in/PressReleasePage.aspx?PRID=1967291&quot;&gt;37%&lt;/a&gt;) in terms of female participation in workspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a vacum of good ideas, weak ones spread. In the absence of mature male figures/voices, and with the ease of spread of ideas on the internet, we left this important topic to a DU freshmen Eng literature student, who herself was going with the vibe on most things. The idea of feminism came on the forefront – and not in the best way. The idea of gender equality rather than positive geneder roles. Somehow and understandably, women became the oppressed class? (instead of the misunderstood and misrepresented ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how did we react? DEI in the west. Women quota in jobs, govt. offices, elections and so much more. More efforts were pushed in the pretend-equality rather than conscious equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we’re on a latter part of this bell-curve now. We’re understanding the limits of those bad ideas and I guess we have a results of the experiments in - Masculintity is not the opposite of Feminity. Boyish immaturitity in the opposite of masculinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shivaji and the Maratha Empire&lt;br /&gt;
On my recent Pune-Mumbai trip, there are a few things that come out very stongly to you:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Celebration of Social Workers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise mentality (as opposed to Startup mentality)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More acceptance of the Indian Freedom struggle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better governance compared to the rest of the country – you see political influence everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sivaji - everywhere and in everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was more intrigued by the #5 more than anything. A political king, rising to the role of state embelem, which never happens everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All cities either die a Kochi or live long enough to become Mumbai.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pune
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a society that has prioritised stablity and a simple life over more complex and competitive life&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mumbai
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a society where a normal human can never feel belonging. when the socity doesn’t work for you, how long can you remain for that society.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I guess, this makes the populus of mumbai to always be running.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it’s a big city and one that can destory someone’s individuality so easily.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parsi society and Parsi Businesses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comformity in a Lifestyle and the death of life&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hedonism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Epicurianism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;c-startup&quot;&gt;C. Startup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bhagwaan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was researching Zappos and few points stuck-out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They had key values that they decided that would direct it’s employees when in doubt: wowing their customers and delivering the best customer service
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They then had 10 core values that drove their company forward – https://www.zappos.com/c/about&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They decided very early on to own each point of impact for their customers – hence moved to warehouse &amp;lt;&amp;gt; delivery model rather than a dropshipping model.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This changed when Dr Marten’s got onboarded into the company – yet again showing how 1 change has everlasting impacts in a company and why a balance of it all usually works.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">tl;dr of the lessons from this month</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Feb 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/02/29/lessons-feb-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Feb 2024" /><published>2024-02-29T03:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-02-29T03:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/02/29/lessons-feb-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/02/29/lessons-feb-2024.html">&lt;p&gt;tl;dr of the lessons from this month&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-from-the-books-im-reading&quot;&gt;A. From the Books I’m Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40549476-this-is-marketing&quot;&gt;This is Marketing by Seth Godlin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Marketing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“People don’t want to buy a quarter-inch drill bit. They want a quarter-inch hole”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Decision matrix: Desire for gain or avoidance of loss.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Perception drives reality.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On user behaviour:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;People are different. Noone is irrational.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some people are looking for a feeling rather than the logical truth &lt;em&gt;and that’s okay.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Everything that we purchase – every investment, every trinket, every experience – is a bargain. That’s why we bought it. Because it was worth more than what we paid for it.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Everything gets easier when you walk away from the hubris of everyone. Your work is not for everyone. It’s only for those who signed up for the journey.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The relentless pursuit of mass will make you boring, because mass means average, it means the centre of the curve, it requires you to offend no one and satisfy everyone.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“When in doubt, assume that people will act according to their current irrational urges, ignoring information that runs counter to their beliefs, trading long-term for short-term benefits and most of all, being influenced by the culture they identify with.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;b-from-the-internet&quot;&gt;B. From the Internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sonder&lt;br /&gt;
The moment when you realise that everyone around you has an internal life as rich and as conflicted as you.&lt;br /&gt;
This feeling leads to greater empathy and kindness about other people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing Thyself&lt;br /&gt;
The discussion of &lt;em&gt;marriage&lt;/em&gt; has commenced in my friend-circle. In all the discussions, 1 direction that I keep leaning on is the act of knowing oneself and reconciling with one’s ying and yang.  &lt;br /&gt;
We are a generation whitewashed by the latest thing, filling our lives with wants that will outlive our human lives. Our spiritual experiences are the material possessions and artificial scarcity has us running around the world. There is so much noise out there that it drowns the authentic, self-voice deep within.&lt;br /&gt;
You will always be confused, lost and forever in the pursuit of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; feeling until you understand yourself well. &lt;br /&gt;
You can’t also let others do that thinking for you, and adopt their conclusions.&lt;br /&gt;
One shortcut that I’ve recently found for this reconciliation of self is writing detailed essays about yourself. I did this activity this month and it made a lot of things clear for myself. The questions that confused me, ideas that eluded me, I could make sense of all of them. Some pointers for the essay: birth, &lt;em&gt;pind&lt;/em&gt; (community, village, hometown), history, values, likes, dislikes, wants, needs, aspirations, ambitions, and goals in life.&lt;br /&gt;
Few additional tools to help you with this:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politicalcompass.org/&quot;&gt;Political Identity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Our lives are run by politics. Of the states’, religion, people, philosophies and much more. The way you think remains constant across these fields.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politicalcompass.org/pdfcertificate?pname=hasime&amp;amp;ec=-1.88&amp;amp;soc=-1.28&quot;&gt;Here’s mine if you’re curious.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/&quot;&gt;Personality Test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I gave the 16Personalites test again. It’s one of the best introspective tools to understand yourself better.  &lt;br /&gt;
I’m a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/entj-personality&quot;&gt;Commander Personality Type&lt;/a&gt; if you’re curious.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circadian_rhythm&quot;&gt;Circadian rhythm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tigerfeathers.substack.com/p/ondc-remixing-commerce?utm_source=Antler+India&amp;amp;utm_campaign=515b89922f-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2021_11_22_07_12_COPY_01&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_term=0_17249004c1-515b89922f-437499216&amp;amp;mc_cid=515b89922f&quot;&gt;ONDC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chop.edu/conditions-diseases/pregnancy-over-age-30&quot;&gt;On Marriage and having kids after 30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prometheus&quot;&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to Greek Mythology, Prometheus was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titans&quot;&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;(older Gods, banished to the underworld) who stole fire from the Olympian Gods and gave it to humanity hence ushering the age of technology and human progression to building civilizations.&lt;br /&gt;
For his crime, he was bound to a rock, with an eagle eating away his liver daily. This was thought of as a form of eternal torment as his liver grew back every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Esoteric Knowledge&lt;br /&gt;
Knowledge intended for or likely to be understood by only a small number of people with a specialised interest.  Today’s businesses are built on esoteric &amp;amp; copious insights that you only get once you get deeper into one field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few other topics that I got into thinking all thanks to the illustrious set of friends that I have and I wish to do dedicated articles on all of them. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rise of Individualism (v/s Collectivism) is a Broken Capitalist Society Phenomenon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI and its impact on Medicine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why Now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auf wiedersehen!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="retro, monthly" /><summary type="html">tl;dr of the lessons from this month A. From the Books I’m Reading This is Marketing by Seth Godlin On Marketing “People don’t want to buy a quarter-inch drill bit. They want a quarter-inch hole” Decision matrix: Desire for gain or avoidance of loss. Perception drives reality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons from Jan 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/01/31/lessons_jan_2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons from Jan 2024" /><published>2024-01-31T09:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2024-01-31T09:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/01/31/lessons_jan_2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/01/31/lessons_jan_2024.html">&lt;p&gt;2024 will be the year. The year when the current deficit running between the new year resolutions and what happens gets reduced. I’ve figured out the missing part afterall – focus and discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus is saying no to things – as much as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is saying no to easy – as much as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of being disciplined, here’s a last ditch effort to put out a blog post on Jan, on the last day of the month at 2:28 AM. :facepalm:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, things I learnt in Jan 2024:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://assets.ctfassets.net/qnesrjodfi80/1SubvPLxCoeImGSwsWE6Iw/999a8da9494c10548c2fd165438668e7/prager-the_missing_tile_syndrome-transcript.pdf&quot;&gt;The Missing Tile Syndrome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coined by Dennis Prager, it talks about how we focus on the missing bits in things rather than focus on the whole part that we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play tricks on ourselves and undermine our happiness; by concentrating on the missing tiles every one of us has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a large extent, the answer to that question will determine how happy you will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freudian_slip&quot;&gt;Freudian Slip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand don’t judge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Good study is when you understand both ends of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doubt can only be replaced with action. [ Ted Lasso S03E01]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can’t let yesterday get in the way of today.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html">2024 will be the year. The year when the current deficit running between the new year resolutions and what happens gets reduced. I’ve figured out the missing part afterall – focus and discipline.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Way of Hashiras (pillars)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/08/16/the-way-of-hashiras-or-pillars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Way of Hashiras (pillars)" /><published>2023-08-16T04:23:08+05:30</published><updated>2023-08-16T04:23:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/08/16/the-way-of-hashiras-or-pillars</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/08/16/the-way-of-hashiras-or-pillars.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-should-do-everything-everyday&quot;&gt;Why you should do everything, everyday.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I’ve stolen the word – “Hashira” from the beautifully animated, a lil rushed but overall great anime : &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demon_Slayer:_Kimetsu_no_Yaiba&quot;&gt;Demon Slayer: Kimetsu no Yaiba&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t seen it, you definitely should. To those unaware, the word “Hashira” means a pillar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that off the way, here’s what the Hashira concept is a metaphor for – &lt;strong&gt;We all live multiple lives. Our mental stability, happiness, and contentment are mostly derived from the stability of these lives.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how you can think of it: imagine a wooden plane raised on top of a few wooden pillars. The plane is a metaphor for the stability of our lives and each pillar, a metaphor for the many unique lives that we have going on ourselves. For some, it is their work-life, for others a relationship, for others their passion projects and so on. Whatever forms of pillars there are, the stability of the wooden plane is utterly dependent on the strength of the pillars that it’s standing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of hustle culture, one mistakes by focusing and relying on only 1 of these lives. The mirage of focus often blinds oneself to the multiverse of possibilities out there. Don’t get me wrong, &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; is needed for some greater purpose but the total no. of people drawing meaning out of that focus are the exceptions and not the rule. For a normal Joe, like me, a unilateral life is a myth, an illusion that we convince ourselves into living. People’s work becomes their identity. Their relationship becomes a marker in their friendship circle. The cause they support becomes their cause of being. As long as it keeps people busy, they are happy living that 1 life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s until these pillars break – people either get laid-off or are not appreciated enough at work, or are burnt out and down goes their entire stability plane. When the source of an identity is lost, one looks for it elsewhere. The collapse of the wooden plane, and the absence of a new pillar to take care of it – instantaneously – results in the fall into the abyss of anxiety, doubt, imposter syndrome, and existential crisis which simmers for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The antidote is simple. 1 pillar structures are seldom strong. Build more pillars. Ideally, 5+ pillars to hold your peace. So that if even one of them breaks or shows weakness or needs maintenance, the others are there to safeguard against the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve in the past made similar mistakes. For the majority of the time, I was a workaholic. I worked till exhaustion, from 8 AM to 1 AM. So much so that Saturdays were blocked lying on the bed, for therapy sessions with &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/artist/56ZTgzPBDge0OvCGgMO3OY&quot;&gt;The Beach House&lt;/a&gt; playlist (Depression Cherry is :ok_hand:).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhausted, I decided to focus more on health – and only health. Work suffered. Back to the Beach House playlist. And then, something else came along and so went the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was until it occurred to me how our brain works. How, dopamine, oxytocin, serotonin and endorphins – chemicals responsible for a good mental state are triggered by unique triggers that are independent of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, my pillars include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my book-reading life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my work life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my “being a good flatmate” life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my relationships life – with friends and family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my side-hustle life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my gym life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my upskilling life .. and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in a completely different mental state nowadays. It’s a mindful phase that I wish upon a lot more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your pillars could look different, and it’s completely okay. What is important is that you need to live them all. All of them, all at once. Growth in all is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these parallel lives complement each other and have long-term effects. All of these are infinite games in a finite structure (a day). The idea is to live an intentional life. The idea is to have a framework where nothing of value, worth the investment is left to the future to take care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naval says – “All the returns in life, whether in wealth, relationships, or knowledge, come from compound interest.” And nothing grows better than daily compounding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">Why you should do everything, everyday.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Lessons in Building a Product</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/07/28/biggest_opportunities_2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Lessons in Building a Product" /><published>2023-07-28T12:03:08+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-28T12:03:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/07/28/biggest_opportunities_2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/07/28/biggest_opportunities_2023.html">&lt;p&gt;I was on my daily post-dinner walk and was listening to @sama’s Lecture 1 about startups and kept hearing the big advice on what and how to startup and the biggest things I heard again and again were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Big problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That you can’t live without&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desperately want others to solve around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, here’s the list of problems that I think people need to solve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plastic Decomposition: Our world is going to be eaten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Hardeep Singh Mehra</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="startup" /><summary type="html">I was on my daily post-dinner walk and was listening to @sama’s Lecture 1 about startups and kept hearing the big advice on what and how to startup and the biggest things I heard again and again were:</summary></entry></feed>